Guide to the Estelle Brodman Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Estelle Brodman Papers
ca.1950-1987.
Brodman, Estelle, 1914-2007
20 linear ft (ca. 14,500 items in 46 boxes).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
MS#0149
4079563
This collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, notes, documents, reports, publications and other printed matter relating to Estelle Brodman, librarian and professor of Medical History.
Biographical Note
Librarian and Professor of Medical History at Washington University in St. Louis MO.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, manuscript notes, reports, conference papers, and related printed materials dealing with her activities as a consultant on documentation for population and family planning libraries and information centers, 1967-1969, her membership on the President's National Advisory Commission on Libraries, 1968-1969, and printed material on Japanese libraries collected in 1962 when she was a visiting professor at Keio University in Tokyo. Dr Brodman was Expert Consultant for Documentation for the Central Family Planning Council in New Dehli in 1967-1968 and Consultant for Documentation at the World Health Organization's Regional Office for South East Asia in New Dehli, in 1970. These "India Files" contain correspondence with Indian officials, UN officials, and long letters with the Washington University Medical Library staff. Also there are reports and related printed material on family planning in India, including material from the All-India Conference on Documentation in Family Planning, 30-31 July 1970. In 1976-1977, Brodman was consultant for the UN Fund for Population Activitiies (UNFPA). Her files contain correspondence with UNFPA officials, UNFPA briefings, reports, working papers, and her notes. Also included are working papers, notes, and related family planning literature from the Association for Population/Family Planning Libraries and Information Centers Development Institute in Bangkok, September 1973.
The National Advisory Commission on Libraries files consist of correspondence, minutes, other working paperes, drafts of its report, and printed material. The Japanese Libraries files are solely printed materials on Japanese libraries, especially academic libraries, and include library journals, library catalogs, and other library publications. Some of these have contributions by Brodman. Also included are manuscripts and related materials on her teaching, research, and publication in the fields of medical libraries, medical librarianship, and medical bibliography, her medical library consultantships in the 1970s and her files as a member of the Missouri Governor's Library Conference, 1978.
1985 ADDITION: Corresponmdence & subject files, 1979-1984, dealing with Brodman's activities since her retirement as a teacher, library consultant, writer, and resident of the Meadow Lake Retirement Village.
1989 ADDITION: Correspondence, subject files, documents, photographs, and videocassettes, 1970-1987, reflecting Brodman's most recent activities in library science and at Meadow Lake Retirement Village (Hightstown, NJ).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in one series:
Series I: Estelle Brodman Papers, 1950-1987
Subjects
All-India Conference on Documentation in Family Planning.; Association for Population/Family Planning Libraries and Information Centers, International.; Central Family Planning Council (New Dehli, India).; Columbia University.--School of Library Service.; Keiō Gijuku Daigaku.; Meadow Lake Retirement Village (Hightstown, N.J.).; Medical Library Association.; Missouri. Governor's Library Conference, 1978.; Regional Centre for Documentation on Human Reproduction, Family Planning and Population Dynamics.; United Nations Population Fund.; United States.--National Advisory Commission on Libraries.; Washington University (Saint Louis, Mo.).--School of Medicine.; India--Population--Study and teaching.; India--Population policy.; Southeast Asia--Population policy.; Bibliography.; Birth control.; Documentation.; Libraries--Japan.; Library science.; Medical libraries.; Medicine--Bibliography.; Population policy.; Universities and colleges--Japan.; Minutes.; Proceedings.; Photographs.; Reports.; Slides.; Video tape.; College teachers.; Consultants.; Educators.; Librarians.; Medical librarians.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1980 M-1980 Brodman, Estelle Gift
Gift of Estelle Brodman, 1980, 1981, 1984 & 1989.
- Series I: Estelle Brodman Papers, 1950-1987
  - College of Physicians and Surgeons History (Box 47)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts and Related Materials on Research, Teaching and Publication (Box 2-5)
    - B-Columbia University. School of Library Service (1) (Box 2)
    - Columbia University. School of Library Service (2) (Box 3)
    - History of the National Library of Medicine (t.ms.) (Box 4)
    - K-W (Box 5)
  - Subject Files (Box 6-8)
    - Courses
      - Health Care Administration Course (Box 47)
      - History of Medicine Course, 1968-1974 (Box 47)
    - Medical Librarianship; Libraries; Medical Library Association (Box 6)
    - Missouri Governor's Library Conference (Box 7-8)
  - India Files (Box 9-11)
    - Correspondence (Box 9)
    - Reports (Box 10)
    - Printed Materials (Box 11)
  - India Files; UNFPA Files (1981 addition)
    - India Files: Printed Materials cont. (Box 12)
    - UNFPA (United Nations Fund for Population Activities)
      - Correspondence; Reports (Box 12)
      - Correspondence; Briefings; Reports (Box 13)
    - APLIC (Association for Population/Family Planning Libraries and Information Centers) Bangkok Seminar, 1973
      - Working Papers; Printed Materials (Box 14)
      - NACL (National Advisory Commission on Libraries, 1968-1969) (Box 15-21)
        - Correspondence (Box 15)
        - Subject Files
          - B-F (Box 15)
          - H-Meeting Transcripts (1-2) (Box 16)
          - Meeting Transcripts (3)-Minutes of Meetings (1) (Box 17)
          - Minutes of Meetings (2)-T (Box 18)
          - Report (Box 19)
          - Printed Materials (Box 20-21)
      - Consultant-ship Files (Box 22-26)
        - Carolina Population Center Technical Information Service (Box 22)
        - Georgetown University Medical Center (Box 23)
        - SUNY Downstate Medical Center (Box 24)
        - Roswell Park Memorial Institute, Buffalo (Box 24)
        - UCLA Cancer Center (Box 25)
        - University of South Alabama Libraries (Box 26)
        - Vanderbilt University Medical Center (Box 26)
      - Japanese Libraries
        - Printed Materials (Box 27-29)
        - Printed Materials cont. (Box 30)
      - Population Slides on Family Planning (Box 30)
      - Printed Materials
        - By Brodman (Box 31)
        - Inscribed to Brodman (Box 31)
        - References to Brodman (Box 31)
  - 1985 ADDITION
    - Correspondence Files
      - General Correspondence, 1983-84 (Box 32)
    - Subject Files
      - Brodman, Estelle- Biographical Materials (Box 32)
      - Brodman, Estelle- Meadow Lake Retirement Home, 1981-84, (2 Folders) (Box 32)
      - Columbia Univ. School of Library Service- Bio-med Communication, 1984 (course by Brodman) (Box 32)
      - Medical Library Association- Oral History Project, 1980-82 (Box 33)
        - Correspondence, A-Z (Box 33)
        - Background Material (Box 33)
      - St. Louis Univ. Medical Center- Survey
        - Background Materials (Box 33)
        - Report (Box 33)
      - Southern Illinois Univ. Medical Library, 1981-82 (Consultant-ship) 3 Folders) (Box 34)
      - Univ. of Alabama Graduate School of Library Science- Research Methodology Workshop, 1982 (taught by Brodman) (Box 34)
      - WHO
        - Office of Libraries... Geneva, 1983- Cataloging Position (Box 34)
        - Western Pacific Regional Office- Bio-medical Information: System Conference, Manila, 1983 (Box 35)
    - Estelle Brodman Lectures (Box 47)
    - Publications (Box 47)
  - 1989 Addition (1970 - 1987)
    - Correspondence Files (Box 36-37)
      - 1982 - '87
        - A - K (Box 36)
        - L - Z (Box 37)
    - Subject Files (Box 38-45)
      - Advisory Health Committee (Box 38)
      - Beaumont, William (Box 38)
      - Columbia University (Box 38)
      - Consortia (Box 38)
      - Cultural and Heritage Commission (Box 38)
      - Curriculum Vitae (Box 38)
      - Curriculum Vitae (Box 47)
      - Drake, Daniel (with related videocassette) (Box 39)
      - Fifth International Congress on Medical Librarianship (with related videocassette, Proceedings and Program) (Box 40)
      - "The Future of Information Systems for the Medical Sciences" Symposium (with related bound volume) (Box 40)
      - Historical Society (Box 41)
      - Honors (Box 41)
      - Hospital Medical Libraries (Box 41)
      - Hospitals and Libraries - Background Data, (2 Folders) (Box 41)
      - Meadow Lakes Retirement Home, T.V. Committee (Highstown, New Jersey) (Box 42)
      - Metro and Other Grant Proposals (Box 42)
      - Miscellaneous Personal (Box 43)
      - New York Academy of Medicine (Box 43)
      - New York Parking Violations (Box 43)
      - Ph.D. Degree (Box 43)
      - Professor's Uncataloged (Box 43)
      - Purse Snatching (Box 43)
      - Research in Health Sciences Libraries (Box 43)
      - Special Libraries Association Dana Award (Box 44)
      - University of Illinois (Box 44)
      - Washington, D.C. (Box 44)
      - Who's Who in America (Box 44)
      - Women in Medicine, (7 Folders) (Box 45)
    - Personal Calendars, Publications and Manuscripts by Brodman and Photographs (Box 46)
      - Works by Brodman:
        - "The Doctor's Tools: From Saddlebag to Hospital" (Box 46)
        - "Hospital Medical Libraries in New York City & Westchester" (2 versions) (Box 46)
        - "Research in Health Sciences Libraries" (2 versions) (Box 46)
        - Preface to Special Collections - Library, Washington University School of Medicine (Box 46)
        - "William Beaumont and the Transfer of Biomedical Information" (Box 46)
      - Two Photographs:
        - Janet Doe (Box 46)
        - Eileen R. Cunningham, Janet and Mary Louise Marshall (ca. 1948) (Box 46)